[Music]
they eat the watermelon
why do they even do that
[Music]
at this point vr chat isn't really new
it's been out in one form or another
since
2014 although it didn't really start to
pick up steam until well
steam not that long after reaching the
platform it fell into the hands of some
streamers
soon after it exploded in popularity if
you don't currently play vr
chat but you've heard of it chances are
you've seen it a meme compilation or
something of the sorts
it has a mixed reputation
which is evident when you scan youtube
for a hot second
if you haven't heard of it explaining it
is pretty simple it's a virtual chat
room where most of the content is user
created
that means that the avatar's world's
experiences it's all created by the
users
so when you see cat girls wolf boys and
many many
many memes know that this wasn't
intentional
no one at vrchat wanted it to be this
way it just is
because that's what the community wants
despite the name however vrchat isn't
just for those with vr headsets it's
for anyone that can run it either on pc
or your headset of choice
while it's best experience in vr plenty
of people stick to desktop mode and
never really leave that i've known about
vr chat myself for years
it's been relatively popular in my group
of friends but
i just never got it i guess that was
until the entire world flipped on its
head
being locked inside can drive you a bit
fatty you can't see your friends
you can't see your family you can't see
anyone you also can't go anywhere
even if you're an introvert it feels
just suffocating
to make a long story short my wife and i
started to spend a lot of time together
in vr chat
what started as just a way to kill time
in the middle of a pandemic
quickly became something more soon we
began to go on
dates to all kinds of exotic and
beautiful places
eventually she wanted to make us both
custom avatars
like they say when in rome i've stuck
just about 100 hours into vr chat now
which to be clear feels like nothing but
it is enough for me to feel very
strongly about one thing in particular
vr chat is magical
your avatar can look any way you want it
to
up to the limitations of your equipment
if you're ugly you can make your avatar
beautiful
if you've just gotten out of bed your
avatar can still be wearing beautiful
clothes and professionally applied
makeup
you can look like a gorilla or a dragon
or a giant talking penis in the
metaverse
spend five minutes walking down the
street and you'll see all of these
so depending on what media you've been
exposed to you're probably going to have
a preconceived notion of what vr chat
actually
is a lot of anime avatars
miles and miles of them wait
in fact this doesn't really feel right
no one wants to watch a bald 30 year old
man
lecture them about vr chat let's change
this up
there we go now where were we
vr chat is a community-based social and
creativity hub
built in the vein of many of its
predecessors like habitat
worlds away active worlds their
or second life the idea is simply to
give people an environment to socialize
or create in and at the end of the day
that's basically it it's a socialization
engine
but an extremely stylish one a few of my
friends asked me
what the point is what is the objective
of vr chat
what kind of game is it and that's the
thing it really isn't a game
although there's certainly games within
it seriously people will straight up
recreate all sorts of games in vr chat
from rpgs to shooters to clones of other
vr hits
but the point of your chat is to just
kind of do whatever you want
so yeah you log in pick your avatar and
then you jump into one of a few hundred
worlds
most of which were created by the users
maybe you meet up with a friend and play
a card game
or maybe you decide to go to a virtual
nightclub maybe you meet some friends
maybe you just have a laugh sometimes
you'll just start up an hours long
conversation about
anything the game client allows you to
hop around virtual worlds pretty
seamlessly
the ui is intuitive and there's just not
that much of a learning curve
on the other hand the game itself is
questionably welcoming
this is a game that is just an
unparalleled mish mesh of creativity
anything you want to create with a few
limits can be here
there are so many worlds that are just
acid trips man
i have seen things i've seen so many
things
and the avatars can span everything from
sentient toilet paper to
as i've said already all sorts of anime
characters some original and
some not and all of that creativity goes
places
it's a chaotic mess it's at times a
performance nightmare
when you let anyone upload avatars and
worlds you're inevitably going to let in
a few things that
aren't exactly nice to be around
much like with that snow crash quote
avatars can basically be anything that
you want
if you can model it you can probably
bring it into vr chat
not all models are created equal though
and while some will perform smoothly
others will bring even the best gaming
pc to their knees
there are in-game safety settings you
can use to prevent
particularly resource intensive avatars
from loading but there are ways to
circumvent that system
and that can lead to a bad time a few
times
i've gotten motion sick due to an
especially malevolent avatar
likewise i've been hit by waves of
screaming children and skyscraper tall
avatars
or swarms of people throwing dead memes
around and
new memes that make me just and
look i know it sounds like i'm
complaining but i think vr chat is truly
what vr was always supposed to be
when i first read snow crash and was
introduced to the metaverse as a kid
vr chat is exactly what i was
envisioning in my head
i've always been obsessed with virtual
reality it's
always just been something i've been
fascinated by sometime in 1996
or 1995 i can't remember my parents
bought me a virtual boy
at the time they'd been discontinued so
they were fairly cheap i remember seeing
it sitting on the end cap of a long gone
toy store
i only had two games and it was complete
garbage but it got my imagination going
like nothing else
as a kid i had to stay home from school
sick quite a bit
as well i didn't know it at the time my
immune system wasn't a big fan of my
intestines that means i spent a lot of
time
on the then developing pre-com boom
internet
that meant geocities and lots of chat
rooms
eventually one day someone suggested to
me what is in my mind anyway
the real predecessor to vr chat active
worlds active worlds is a 3d chat
program launched in 1995 as an
offshoot of another project by worldsync
who'd previously developed another
semi-3d
chat program called worlds chat
eventually active worlds would spin off
into its own company due to internal
interest issues
that's probably a good thing as their
parent company became
known as notorious patent trolls active
world's big difference
was that whereas worlds chat was all
built by developers
active worlds was built by users this
building was done by moving around
in-game objects
it would be a stretch to call this
proto-unity
but it works in a very similar way you
use shapes put textures on those shapes
and then move them into place
there's a rudimentary scripting language
to modify objects with in a variety of
ways too
active worlds was basically built like a
web browser you'd spawn in a gateway
that was basically just a general chat
room through the ui
you could teleport to different worlds
some of these worlds were hosted by
individual people on their own servers
others however were referred to as
public worlds one of these public worlds
alpha world was the largest and usually
the most populated with a few hundred
users at any given time these particular
worlds were hosted by
active worlds themselves and were
basically just free-for-alls
in alpha world anyone could make
buildings this led to the world being
filled
by all kinds of creations some
incredible some not so incredible
the big draw at back to worlds was that
you could quite literally
build communities people would come to
this program to make friends and build
things
often at the same time it was genuinely
really cool
and way ahead of its time there are
whole cities here
built by communities that formed in this
world and
when i say cities i don't mean that you
click a button and
a city pops out or there's some kind of
system for setting one up there isn't
someone just decided one day i want to
build a city
the developers never intended for this
to happen it was never encouraged or
forced
someone just wheeled it into being but
active worlds hasn't really stood the
test of time
it's clunky it doesn't perform well and
while many of the in-game creations
still hold up
it doesn't look good it's also abandoned
the company behind aw has a pretty
tumultuous history
and i'm not gonna go into it here it was
also limited by the technology of the
time
you could always tell that there was
more that they wanted to do
but they just couldn't afford to add
features at the time though
active worlds was the coolest thing i
met people from all over the world i
created things joined and built
communities myself i was part of a city
i lived an entire life here one where i
could escape how shitty my body
constantly felt as a kid
for a very large part of my
developmental years my creativity ran
wild in this place
everything about aw is a relic of its
time
the way the game works the things that
were created even what the default
avatars look like
and the fact that they're called avatars
in the first place all of this harkens
back
to a different age and honestly it's an
age that i miss
see while active worlds came out way too
early to be vr
i felt that it truly got with virtual
reality where the metaverse
was always supposed to be i've
referenced snow crash and its metaverse
a few times so far
and i realize that not everyone is
familiar with that particular novel
so for starters snow crash is a novel
that came out in 1992 written by neil
stephenson
it's one of those books that's hugely
influential on the internet
virtual reality and just technology in
general in snow crash
stevenson built basically two separate
worlds first there was reality
reality in snow crash is a cyberpunk
capitalist nightmare where the us has
collapsed and has been subsumed by
numerous corporate entities
then there's the metaverse the metaverse
is a virtual reality plane you log into
a future internet built by hackers and
artists it's still
very much influenced by the real world
but there's a sense that all the
creativity and community
that is perpetually denied in reality
actually has a place there
but the metaverse isn't smooth it's not
a flawless polished experience
it's noisy and loud with planes crashing
on the street
and as mentioned above giant penises
walking around next to meticulously
crafted avatars
sure the corporate trappings are still
present but they don't run the place
that's kind of the whole point cyberpunk
is often described as
high tech low life and i feel like a
mishmash of art next to absolute havoc
is really on point that really captured
something about the early internet
sandwiched between the yuppie runaway
capitalism of the 80s
and the hopefulness and technophilia of
the 90s
a lot of cyberpunk literature reflects
that and
i think it's really telling that the
same corpus is constantly referenced in
virtual reality games or in aws case
proto-vr games snow crash was very much
cyberpunk
technically post cyberpunk go away
english degree
neil stephenson was clearly looking at
the then 90s internet as a place of both
potential
and well giant corporations taking
everything over
even though that hadn't happened quite
yet but heavy on the potential
was really the important bit there
oftentimes the point of cyberpunk gets
lost in modern media
take cyberpunk 2077 for example while we
don't really know what it's like yet
a lot of what the developers have said
reflect that whole high-tech low-life
maxim
without really seeming to understand
that the comma in that phrase is a
critique
i think that stay dead you can't hurt me
anymore
active worlds was the perfect
representation of the metaverse and it's
no wonder the team that built active
worlds was certainly inspired by the
book
and not just the book but the sort of
ethos that was behind it
there's always this sort of cynicism
present within a lot of new technology
that just doesn't feel present in aw
or at least didn't at the time there's
always the secret hand that's trying to
monetize in the most aggressive way
even if that means functionally changing
what makes something special
active worlds was devoid of that in many
ways it seemed like it was a project in
building something cool
and just seeing what players did with it
essentially it was an experiment in
building the metaverse and just seeing
what would happen
but the virtual communities that came
after their and second life
specifically always seemed not
that while second life developed a
reputation
there was always something more
streamlined more polished more corporate
about that particular app
that kept me away from it whereas active
worlds was a mess
second life was streamlined and built
more like a pre-social network than
anything else
in active worlds you had to find and
build a community in the most
jankiest obtuse way possible in second
life by comparison
they kind of rolled out the red carpet
for you that same thing can be said with
their
which was an absolute abomination a
corporate fever dream that saw what was
happening in virtual worlds
and said someone in a boardroom go hey
what if we sold this to mtv
really what was going on with virtual
worlds was the same thing that was
happening with the internet at large
it was changing while it arguably was
becoming more useful
it was also becoming more boxed in there
was a certain playfulness
along with a strong sense of community
that just seemed to be lost
all right zoomers old man straz is here
to tell you about the good old days
get on your swim trunks because we're
about to surf the net
get in your lanyard and slap on your
driving gloves because it's time to
cruise the world wide web
no but seriously the internet in 2020
is a wonderful thing i'm not going to
pretend like it isn't
the sheer amount of information the ease
at which you can access it and the tools
available at our fingertips
are bizarre and wonderful we're living
in the future
baby we're also right in the middle of
the apocalypse and the modern internet
lets us
basically order anything we want
straight to our doors
the internet is without a doubt easier
to use more straightforward
more useful and more prominent than it
ever has been in the past
this is an obvious statement to be blunt
but i feel like it's necessary to make
before i say the next thing
in the famous words of grammy award
winner rob thomas
man it's a hot one the internet is
also really really bad at one time
not that long ago the internet just
didn't look like the internet we know
and love
at one time the internet wasn't the
fabric holding together your social
circle nor was it the thing ensuring
your food got there on time
that might seem bad but it also wasn't
something that manipulated our thoughts
constantly sold us things harvested our
data willy-nilly
let elon musk say anything
invaded our lives with countless
algorithms or just a billion other
really crimey scummy things
comparing the modern internet to the
internet of the past is a bit like
comparing a main street in most towns 20
years ago
to main street today there's tactically
more stuff there now
probably and it's probably more useful
but
a lot of the charm and uniqueness that
made it special
just isn't there anymore the modern
internet is a
giant funko pop it's a miserable twisted
corporate simulacrum of ideas
conjured up into plastic nonsense that
you can collect and tag
it's miserable cynical a year ago i
bookmarked a comment on reddit that i
liked just so much the randomness of the
old internet
it felt like it was truly run by the
people now it feels super
corporate and designed everything is
planned
we're like two minutes into this section
and i realize i'm being pretty vague
so let me say that when i say early
internet i specifically mean the decade
from about 94 to 2004.
this is the period that the internet
really started to evolve from something
academic
to well whatever people wanted to do
with it
this meant early venture capitalist
failures in the dot-com boom but it also
meant fan sites
early forms springing up from the corpse
of bulletin board systems or bbs's
and an unstopped wave of creativity and
community building
there weren't any real expectations for
what you could or should create
it was just a blank slate but the thing
is for a long time
the internet wasn't really user friendly
and that meant that people
not necessarily corporations were the
ones to fill in the gaps
you'd have bookmarks did people even use
those anymore like
like thousands of bookmarks to just
random individual sites that people
built in their basement to help you do
random things college professors used to
maintain sites on their individual
interests
and those were usually the best places
for information
like if you enjoyed a tv show or a video
game you'd go to a website for that
video game
and that's where everything was and
there were like 10 other websites just
like that
and they'd all link to each other and
they'd have these little buttons you'd
click on to get to the other sites there
are web rings you
don't even use a search engine you would
just find a web ring portal
which was a bunch of sites that were
linked together and you would click
around it was novel
it wasn't efficient but as you jumped
from site to site
there was a distinct sense of
personality you
really would surf the web you would
really discover new places and things
and
people and there was no algorithm or
anything doing it for you
you were doing that work today the
internet isn't really a thing you
explore
it's just a delivery system it's a way
for us to get to our apps or websites
that might as well
just be abs i'm not excluding myself
here either
most days i don't really explore the
internet
the internet is just the thing that
gives me access to reddit or twitter or
gmail
i can't honestly remember the last time
i visited someone's personal website
like zoomers if if you're still there
did did you know that people can just
have websites that they
used to just have websites just like
websites for stuff not portfolios or
pictures of their cat
just like stuff you'd find but all of
that over the last two decades
has been transformed giant corporate
overlords have soaked up basically
all of the internet for better or worse
google for example vacuumed up so much
of the search space
that there basically aren't any other
search engines that matter
that control fundamentally means that
they dictate how the internet works and
what succeeds and what doesn't
their algorithm determines what you see
this is true
for every website that houses user
created content of any kind
the algorithm theoretically directs
people to what they want to see
but more accurately it directs them to
content that keeps them engaged on the
platform
so they have more of a chance to see the
advertisements
that's why youtube likes long content
you're more likely to stick around for
advertisements if you're on one
continuous video
but of course the content has to also be
advertiser friendly
if it isn't you'll need an alternative
source of revenue
and while it's great that many channels
have been able to do that
there's no doubt that this molds what
content is on the platform
for every h bomber guy or tentacruel
there are a thousand
garbage top 10 channels or life hacks or
unboxings or
whatever just because the algorithm eats
that stuff up
i mean christ i i go on youtube to get
away from churned out corporate media
and now i'm being served recommendations
for jimmy kimmel
i'm not saying that everything created
today on youtube is bad
far from it but what it is in almost
every case
is creativity that's been boxed in by
exactly what a specific corporate
overlord wants
and while creativity can live within
closed off
walled in spaces and maybe even that
strict form can produce
really great art it's still limiting in
a way that's just
chafed against me that i just didn't
realize until
fairly recently to put it another way
the introduction of web 2.0 was supposed
to usher in a new age of
community-based websites and
user-created content
and for a short period of time it did in
the early 2000s you saw the growth of
sites like newgrounds deviantart ytm d
and even dig yet not that long after
social media took over and as the
dot-com boom
faded in the mirror dollar signs once
again appeared in investors eyes
internet mainstays died replaced by new
corporate behemoths
who were restructuring the web to suit
their margins
while there were brief moments of the
older internet living on in these
formats
once again like myspace and even the
older live journal
xanga and whatnot they were quickly
crowded out
hell even the bits of absurdist
creativity that
somehow appeared on social media quickly
turned into
this there are likely to be
people yelling at their screen now that
this is just what people wanted
no one forced facebook on them but
i'm really not so sure it's hard to
teleport back to that time
but what these technologies promised at
the time
and what they became are really not the
same thing
likewise even implying that users really
have genuine agency
in this sort of thing is
that's for another video but is someone
that works in marketing
and sees how the sausage is made yeah
no there's obviously a nostalgia for
this particular era for
folks my age being that we are
millennials
but i don't think that it was just all
nostalgia
i was a huge nerd surprise in high
school
and i'd always have kids asking me to
help them make their own website
it wasn't because they wanted to be rich
they just wanted a place to put their
music or art or
inside jokes or whatever on the flip
side i have a cousin who asked me
how to go about monetizing his music and
youtube channel
he's like 13. there's a certain way he
looks at the internet
as a tool a business object that i
totally get
but also god that's horribly depressing
for us for those of us that saw the 90s
and early 2000s internet
it just was something totally different
it meant something different
the old internet was a wild west of
wonky
half-baked design and novices barely
scraping together
snippets of html and css and php
and like photoshop skill but probably
more accurately paint shop pro skill
it was a mess crafted from paper mache
and dreams but
it was beautiful and representative of a
different time
when you found a tacky website you knew
it was that way
because someone wanted it that way it
was intentional
the disheveled mess of the
pre-dot-com-era internet was
really bad in a lot of ways but it was
also just so
full of possibility and while i've said
and will continue to say
creativity about a hundred thousand
times it was also about community
active worlds was in many ways perfectly
representative
of that time i think virtual reality and
the sense of stuff like the metaverse
and snow crash
was specifically born out of the chaotic
mess the internet was in its early era
other programs sanitized it much in the
same way that the internet itself was
changed in the mid-2000s
active worlds represented that perfectly
though even though it wasn't technically
virtual reality it was the metaverse
just before the technology had a chance
to
really get the full way there it was a
creative playground a massive community
and just
a space where you could make anything or
be anything
just because you wanted to it was
genuinely beautiful
and up until recently i thought that
that particular vision
wasn't something i'd ever find again
vr chat isn't something that i
immediately fell in love with in fact
vrchat sat installed on my computer from
way back when i got my first vr headset
the htc vive i i just didn't get it at
first
i walked around wondered what the fuss
was about and then logged right off
why would i want to talk to random
people on the internet
what is there even to see here now a
quick aside
i think my initial reaction is due to my
own internal
two-point owing well i've always been
into these
creative sort of games or whatever you
want to call them i'm
also a very competitive person i played
a lot of counter-strike wow arena
overwatch here's the storm and so on for
a long time my default
gaming attitude has basically just been
to compete
but when you're 31 and your reaction
speed is starting to slow
you can either deal with it by
gracefully ducking out and admitting
your limitations
find a way to improve your game sense to
compensate or just
internally continue to think you're a
god and instead hide within a virtual
reality filled with cat girls
considering i've been locked in my house
for the last uh 20
000 years or so at this point i i needed
to get out somehow i
just needed to not look at my walls
anymore
it was much the same for my wife and one
day we
just decided to give vr chat another try
and
this time it felt different my second
go-around had me spending some time
interacting with the world
and all the people in it i spent a lot
of time in public worlds which meant
that i was interacting with a pretty
large cross-section of the game's player
base every time i'd take off my headset
i'd look at my wife and just think
holy [__] this is magical yet i couldn't
really put my finger on why
was it just the social interactions was
it just the people i was meeting
i mean yeah of course but there was
something more to it
i've interacted and been in hundreds of
online communities over the years
what was different here what was
different about
vr chat part of it was yeah the the
people the community
there's no algorithm directing me to a
lobby there's no decision making going
on beyond my own
oh this world looks neat when you click
and there you are
right there's nothing else to it the end
result was that i've met people from
many many countries my friends list is
ludicrously diverse
i met people in italy the netherlands
spain france germany russia
saudi arabia the philippines korea japan
and
many many more i've had long
conversations about
politics religion video games anime the
weather
memes the nature of consciousness poop
knives music
performing i i've had so many just good
conversations
and as an aside i've missed that how had
i forgotten that i
enjoyed this that i used to love this
thing but in the web 2.0 era
that was eradicated sure facebook groups
exist
twitter can theoretically connect you
with other people and read it
but these services are built to put like
with like the realities of that sort of
thing have been
think piece to death typically in
regards to stuff like politics
but i kind of want to build beyond that
and maybe less seriously
like i just think outside of how that's
damaged the world
it's also just ruined this quaint little
experience
the experience of meeting random people
and just talking with them
and to be clear this wasn't something
that just changed over time or was
accidentally broken
it was done on purpose the climate on
social media isn't a bug
it's a feature and once again this is a
topic way too complex to go on a tangent
on and
i've done too many of those already but
yeah the way social media encourages
both division and
like meeting like is not accidental and
it has undoubtedly made the internet a
worse place
but vr chat isn't just the people it's
also about the things they create
and vr chat is full of beautiful
incredible things
some of the worlds people have created
in vr chat are utterly breathtaking
what people are able to do on this
platform is amazing and the thing is
you're probably watching this right now
on a 2d screen and it's
probably still gorgeous to you now
consider that these are virtual
realities that you can go and explore
and interact with it's
really just something else i've probably
played every major vr release on the
market at this point and while there are
plenty of games that deliver memorable
experiences
none do it with the rapid-fire intensity
that vr chat does
i think five or ten years from now many
of the people building hobby creations
in vrchat are going to be working at
major studios or
winning awards somewhere and yes
galleries of beautiful things exist
elsewhere
but just not quite like this and the
creativity isn't just in the creation of
worlds it's
also in the avatars themselves there are
so many that are so neat
there's like an entire virtual fashion
in vr chat and trends and
people who push those things really hard
and then there's the things people do
with those worlds and avatars i've
watched someone dj a psytrance set in vr
i've watched dancing genuinely
impressive dancing i even met a
choreographer in vrchat that took pride
in making routines within virtual
reality
i've had a two foot tall anime boy in a
onesie
pajama thing perform an improv dance
routine in front of me
using his custom avatar a lot of these
things
are often broken and messy and they
glitch out and they aren't always there
they require digging and seeing a lot of
objectively strange and unsettling
things but the thing is
you see people's work too you see the
learning process
you see the janky worlds and the broken
avatars some of which glitch out in
hysterical ways
all this would have been blocked off
somewhere else all of this would have
been
just swept out into a bin it would have
been polished and
optimized it would have been flattened
and streamlined but not here
it's a paradise of high effort [__]
posts
i've taken a ride on a hot dog with
glitched out clipping music screaming in
the background i've had a stick of
butter give me a lap dance it's
insanity actual insanity and there's no
other place like this on the internet
there's no place like this period
anymore
and look i know i know creative places
exist creativity is all over the
internet but these days even creativity
seems organized and structured
treated to the same algorithmic soup
that runs the rest of the internet
i don't want deviantart i want the old
deviantart give me the messy form give
me the disorganized gallery
the old internet was like this active
worlds was like this
there was no real sense to it and
there's still art there
that's long been buried into digital
sand the entropy of failed hard drives
likely killing many a creation before
they were seen by anyone
there are thousands of worlds i'll never
visit all of them and maybe to some
that's a tragedy
maybe there should be some sort of
algorithm that shows me the ones that
are
most organized most optimized cleanest
and most artistic
but i don't want that i want the
postmodern chaotic soup that
birthed the impossible to explain
websites and wonderfully bizarre
creations like
why tmnd that primordial soup is what
created the soul of the internet
and for so long it's been banished in
favor of one-page websites and
endless software-as-a-service clones but
vrchat brings the mess back
i'm sure that seems like a backhanded
compliment
but it isn't hundreds of applications
and games and
relaunches of games have tried so hard
to recapture what made that era
wonderful
the community of it the sense of awe and
wonder the genuine feeling of logging in
and not knowing what you'll find today
of who you'll meet of what you'll see of
what memories you'll make
there's no psychological tooling at play
there's no skinner's box there's no
algorithm
this this right here is what was lost
earlier i mentioned that the current
internet is just a delivery service
well the old one was too but it's what
it's delivering you to
that's the difference the old internet
was a playground of endless possibility
and yes
obviously people were trying to make
money on it and it was commodified and
sliced up by corporations then too
but there was at least the illusion of
choice of creative freedom the new
internet is built to be a frictionless
experience
it's designed in every way to monetize
every click every movement of your mouse
virtually the last two or even three
decades have been entirely defined by
the simple question
how can we possibly squeeze more money
out of this internet thing
and that's led to so many issues so many
deep problems
that'll take god generations to solve it
makes me feel silly
complaining about losing the old
internet or whatever
and yet as silly as it might be logging
into vrchat makes me feel excited in a
way that i have it in years
vrchat is magical because of that it
gets me excited about the internet again
it successfully fools me if just for
this moment in history
this time freezing quarantine that yes
the internet is a wonderful place full
of possibility and
i know practically it's never been
easier to be creative on the internet
than this moment in time
but that creativity always seems like
it's designed to go somewhere
to lead to a job or monetization somehow
and i know i even mentioned future
developers earlier
but that was more of a nod to the talent
of people on this platform
than anything else everyone playing this
game who wants to create an avatar or
world has to pick up unity and blender
and learn a whole set of skills that is
practically useless to them
but it means that they can create an ad
to this world
that they can show off to friends that
they can build communities that are
absurd anywhere else and the thing is i
know i'm not the only one who feels this
way i've seen the general thought of
vr chat feels like the old internet many
many times by
fellow users so honestly my advice is
this
if you do miss that old internet give
vrc a try
i think you'll get it if you spend some
time with it likewise
if you don't know what i'm talking about
and never got to experience that
firsthand
well give it a try too and if you do
like what you see
know that those of us now entering our
30s
are beyond excited for you to get to
experience what we did for the first
time
vrchat is magical it's the absurdity of
the metaverse
it's the beauty of the old internet it's
like hopping into a time machine
but also going to the future merging
and i should i'd write a steins gate
reference
got the microphone ah
god man it's gonna be fun lining that
one up
so if you're wondering if all of my
videos presuming there's gonna be
more than just this one anyway if you're
assuming that all of my videos are gonna
be this cheesy yes
the answer is yeah this is all i know i
this this is what you're gonna get
there's two things that i think are
really left that i haven't had a chance
to get to
just yet and i kind of want to address
them before
closing things out the first thing is
like what about the other
vr worlds the other vr programs that
exist what about them
obviously vr chat isn't the only one
that's out there and so
doesn't everything i just say apply to
them too now i'm talking about things
like any land and art space and
sansar and even something like rec room
or whatever thing zuckerberg is
cooking up the thing is they all
have their merits i'm not going to tell
you that i don't think that some of them
are cool too
the thing is is i think they're
fundamentally cool for different reasons
they bring
something interesting to the table
sansar really does
seem for example like it's gonna really
kill those
virtual events i shouldn't do that with
a microphone
there's also some of the other ones that
i haven't really mentioned or touched on
that do things like use bitcoin
and cryptocurrency to
make vr better
and obviously i think that there's neat
stuff about all of these but they all
are kind of coming at the problem
in a weird way and when i say the
problem i mean this
sort of thing that i think vr chat is so
good at which is
creating communities i think when you
look at it
all of these places are sort of trying
to create a community from
the ground up in a very manufactured
sort of way
like to look at it in a different light
vr chat
basically the developers of vr chat they
never intended for things to be this way
i mean like i said that early on
when vr chat was started the developers
never said let's get a bunch of weebs
together
and create paradise for them
they basically just created a program
and
fertilized it and just said okay
whatever community appears we'll do our
best to nourish and that's exactly what
they did it's what has basically
happened
when a bunch of weebs did come along and
it became
you know de facto for everyone to have
anime avatars or
whatever they just kind of went with it
and they did a fantastic job of taking
that community
that was naturally occurring in their
app and
making sure that it had somewhere to
grow they never intended from day one to
build that community
but when it did appear they made sure
that they
supported it you can kind of draw a
parallel to
here is actually esports
strangely enough if you look at a lot of
games these days they're kind of
built from the ground up with this idea
that we're going to
invent an esport basically every game
that comes out they talk about
tournaments and whatnot when in reality
the best and most successful games in
that particular field
kind of happen organically and a lot of
the times when you just try to build
something from the ground up to
be a certain way well it just doesn't
work
man who would be a fan of an astroturf
esports league
oh [__] the most successful esports were
organic
counter-strike for example that
basically was
a slow build over 20 years valve
never thought it would turn into what it
did but you kind of see where that's
gone
really that's what i see for many of
these competitors
like sansar which i was talking about
before they really want to be
the virtual nightclub space but like i
showed you that kind of exists in vr
chat
and there's a thriving community there
i've been to many
vr raves which is not something i
thought i would ever
say look at me do i look like the kind
of person that goes to a rave
regardless vr chat kind of has that
special thing which
they they found a community and they ran
with it that's just not something you
see nowadays
everything that's built like that reddit
quote said from earlier
is planned from the very beginning it's
we're gonna put this community
in this app that we're making this app
for this community and
it makes sense why things are that way
i'm not saying that they
shouldn't be it's just that i think that
is one of the things that makes vr chat
magical
i also just think and this is kind of
smaller part of that is that most of
those spaces
have been sort of sanitized and i always
feel bad
saying that because i don't necessarily
think that moderation is a bad thing
but yeah for all space it's very clearly
supposed to be something a tad bit more
corporate
and yeah to lead into whatever crazy
contraption zuckerberg is creating
i don't i don't know i don't know i
don't know
realistically it's gonna be bad and the
reason it's gonna be bad
well just go back and watch that section
about there
oh i gotta fix my anime cat over here
oh oh good enough
good enough now to the bigger one
it's monetization we have to look at the
fact that vrchat
realistically needs to make money
currently
vr chat is basically sustained by
investor funds
now investor funds are great they
basically let you build a team and let
you build the thing that you want to
build
without having to worry too much about
anything other than building it
but eventually those investors are going
to want their money back
and they're going to want to see a
profit and this is where
many people get kind of antsy about vr
chat
most of the things in the video that we
just talked about
went from good to
bad because of monetization
this is the literal billion dollar
question which is how do you manage to
sustain a platform
while keeping the feel of the platform
and to be perfectly honest much bigger
programs much bigger things
and communities than vr chat have
totally failed at this
[Music]
i honestly don't know what the answer to
monetization
is and i'm not going to try and guess at
what it could be
what i am going to say is that there's
almost no doubt that no matter what they
decide to do
it's going to fundamentally just change
the platform
you can't basically had a price tag on
something and expect it to remain the
same
but there's gonna have to be one
eventually
having met many of the people on the vr
chat team
i believe at the very least they are
going to try their best but
who can say i can't sit here and tell
you that they're going to come
out with some magical solution that is
going to allow vr chat to stay
as it is today forever and
that's kind of why i made this video to
be perfectly honest
i don't know if vr chat's going to stay
the same forever
so this is what i'll leave you with vr
chat
is magical it combines ideas from
decades ago with the pizzazz of the
2000s
with technology that never existed
really at least not to most people like
five years ago five ten years ago with
the advent of virtual reality
or mainstream virtual reality and even
if you don't have virtual reality even
if you like take the virtual reality bit
and
put it over there or something just the
the freedom to create and create in a
meaningful place and
with the amount of power that unity
through vr chat gives you
is just it's amazing it's a magical
place
that is not just the creativity that
spawns within it
but is the community that essentially
puts all these things together
and does stuff with them however like i
hinted at
i'm not quite sure that it's going to be
this way forever i hope
that the developers are able to maintain
this sense of wonderment
that it just bestows upon me but
in the case that it doesn't i would
really like to
invite other people to experience the
same thing
that i have experienced and so with that
if do you have the time go download vr
chat give it a whirl hop
in you like me might not get it at first
you might end up walking around and
saying
this isn't for me and maybe in a couple
months you'll get the bug
like i did and come back and just be
blown away
regardless thank you for watching
this was a fun journey maybe
i'll make another one
goodbye
[Music]
um
so
you